Guide to the Nelson Morpurgo Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Nelson Morpurgo collection
1918-1940
GEN MSS 493
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.21
(1 box)
The collection consists of manuscripts, correspondence and other papers pertaining to Morpurgo's literary career, including manuscripts of Il fuoco delle piramidi (1923) and several poems.
Morpurgo, Nelson, 1899-1978
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Source information is recorded on the folders. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
NELSON MORPURGO, 1899-1978
Nelson Morpurgo was born in Cairo in 1899, studied law and jurisprudence in France and Italy, and began the practice of law in Cairo in 1933. After World War II he became legal advisor to the Italian Consulate in Egypt, and later was a founder of and advisor to the Italian Chamber of Commerce in Egypt.
Morpurgo is best known as a Futurist author and as a friend of Filippo Marinetti. His publications include Morfina (1921); Il fuoco del Piramidi (1923); and Per le mi donne (1932). After his retirement in Rimini, Morpurgo organized a conference on Futurism and participated in the celebration of the centenary of Marinetti's birth in 1976. He died in Rimini on October 11, 1978.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to Nelson Morpurgo, acquired by the library from a variety of sources. Series I, Accession of May 2001, contains typescripts of poems by Morpurgo and a photograph. Materials added to the collection since that time are located in Series II, Additions since July 2002, listed in the order in which they were added.
Futurism (Literary movement); Italian literature -- 20th Century; Morpurgo, Nelson, 1899-1978
- Accession of May 2001, Series I
  - MORPURGO, NELSON
    - "Ghirigori", [1940] (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Typescript of poem.
      Acc #: 20010406-j
    - "Martirio;" "Soffio;" and "Treno;" [Cairo], [ca. 1932] (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Typescript pages of poems, corrected and marked for printer.
      Acc #: 20010406-i
    - "Non mi sento bene. Poesia chromatica", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      AMS of poem in two colors of ink.
      Acc #: 20010406-m
    - "Notte fra i palmeti;" [Cairo], [ca. 1920?] (Box 1, Folder 4)
      AMS of poem.
      Acc #: 20010406-l
    - Photograph (postcard) of Nelson Morpurgo attending a Fascist march in Milan (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Stamped: "Luigi Betti...Fotografo Livorno"
      Acc #: 20010406-k
- Additions Since July 2001, Series II
  - ACCESSION OF APRIL 2003
    Purchased on the Edwin J. Beinecke Fund and through a gift from the Sonia Raiziss Giop Fund through the Library Associates, 2003
    Acc #: 20030409-b
    - Correspondence
      - TL carbon to the editor of La Bourse Egyptiennes; Cairo, 1938 Mar 5 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - TL carbon to the editor of Varietés; Cairo, 1938 Mar 3 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Writings
      - "4 novembre", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
        Typescript carbon, corrected
      - "Un'avventura 'by night'", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Il fuoco delle piramidi, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 10)
        Holograph
      - "Incontro con Marinetti", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
        Typescript, corrected, incomplete
      - "Intervista", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
        2 typescript carbons, one corrected and one incorporating the corrections
      - "Italia 1949: impressioni di viaggio" (Box 1, Folder 13)
        Typescript, corrected
      - "Marinetti il futurismo ed io", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
        Typescript
      - "Marinetti in egitto (1938)", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - "I miei amici futuristi", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
        Typescript, corrected and signed
      - "Thermometre egyptien", 1933 (Box 1, Folder 17)
        Typescript with holograph additions, signed and dated
      - Unidentified fragment, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
        Typescript, incomplete (play?)
    - Other Papers
      - Menu for a "Futurist" meal at "Celestino" in Cairo, 1930 Jun 3 (Box 1, Folder 19)
        Holograph, illustrated, signed by several of the participants, including Morpurgo, Gino Grossi, Umberto Spallanzani, and Umberto Ricci
      - Photograph of group of men and women, [ca. 1918] (Box 1, Folder 20)
        Includes Morpurgo
      - Photograph group portrait of Italian men in Cairo, [1930] (Box 1, Folder 21)
        Includes Morpurgo; signatures of some members on verso
      - Printed: La Semaine egyptienne, 1932 Oct 31 (Box 1, Folder 22)
        Contains article by Jean Moscatelli about Morpurgo, p. 11
      - Printed: tickets for a performance of Morfina!, 1921 Oct 16 (Box 1, Folder 23)
        With printed notices of performance on verso
      - Printed: legal file holder pertaining to the firm of C. Morpurgo and M. Castro, Cairo (Box 1, Folder 24)
        Annotated: "Scritti di papa. Nelson Morpurgo."
      - Printed: empty envelope decorated with engraving of skull and motto, "Non morior" (Box 1, Folder 25)